这是我们的草图，让我们看看这些函数的类型。
This is our sketch, and let's look at the type of these functions.
所以现在我有了一个函数，它返回一个任务，
So now I have a thing that's a function, it returns a task,
它不需要任何东西并返回一个任务。
it takes nothing and returns a task.
持有另一个接受任务的函数，持有另一个
Holding another function that takes a task, holding another
接受任务的函数，我们在这里得到了这种递归类型。
function that takes a task, we've got this recursive type here.
所以这很有趣，这个怎么样？
So that's interesting, how about this one?
同样的事情，它是一个返回任务的函数
Same exact thing, it's a function that returns a task that's
持有一个返回任务的函数，和 start 一样，好吗？
holding a function returning a task, same with start, okay?
如果我们决定调用这些东西怎么办。
What if we decide to call these things.
现在，我们知道会发生什么。
Now, we know what happens.
现在它是一个返回任务的函数。
Now it's a function that returns a task.
我省略了错误方面。
I'm omitting the error side.
就像任务就像错误和总和一样。
Like task is like error and sum value.
所以让我们只关注任务持有什么，任务持有另一个
So let's just focus on what the task is holding though, task is holding another
任务，它持有另一个任务，它持有另一个任务。
task, which is holding another task, which is holding another task.
但这是菜单，当我们在函数中调用它时，是的，成为任务，对吗？
But this is menu, when we call it in the function, yeah, becomes the task, right?
所以它是测试保持任务的递归数据结构。
So it's a recursive data structure of test holding tasks.
所以我碰巧知道如果我们专注于任务，那是一回事。
So I happen to know if we specialize task, that's one thing.
但是如果我们把它变成任何旧的 monad，我们就明白了吗？
But if we turn this into any old monad, we get we get that right?
如果我们拿 unit 说它需要任何回报，
And if we take unit and say it takes any a returns that,
我们可以开始以不同的方式看待这些类型，对吗？
we can start to look at thes types in different ways, right?
有一种叫做 Fix 的类型。
There's a type called Fix.
让我们看看我们是否可以，嗯，修复的类型就像修复 f，
Let's see if we can, well, the type of fix is like Fix f,
f (Fix f)，所以我们可以说，f 是某个函子。
f (Fix f), so we can do and say, f is some functor.
所以在这种情况下，它就像任务。
So in this case, it's like Task.
然后就是任务（修复任务）。
And then it would be Task (Fix Task).
而修复点只是承诺我们会在某个时候结束。
And the fix point just kinda promises we're gonna hit a end at some point.
我们将找到这个函子的固定点。
We'll hit a fix point of this functor.
您可以继续向下递归，直到它最终结束。
You can keep recursing down until it finally ends.
所以这是一个选择。
So that's an option.
但是我知道的关于修复的一件事是我们今天没有谈论这个。
But one thing I do know about fix is we didn't talk about this today.
我只是在看类型。
I'm just looking at the types.
但我现在要排除修复的原因是因为它
But the reason I'm gonna rule out fix right now is because it
必须持有一个 traversable 才能在其中做一些实际的 monadic 东西。
must hold a traversable to be able to do some actual monadic stuff inside it.
因为 task 是一个 monad 而不是一个函子，
And since task is a monad and not a functor,
我们将把它用作一个 monad。
we're gonna be using it as a monad.
我要后退了，但事实证明 fix 有一个非常近的亲戚叫 free。
I'm gonna back away, but turns out fix has a very close relative called free.
那是一个单子。
And that is a monad.
成为 monad 是一件很幸福的事情。
And it's very happy to be a monad.
这就是递归类型。
And it's this recursive type.
所以它要么是这种递归类型的自由 monad 要么是纯的。
And so it's either this recursive type of a free monad or pure.
所以马上，看看函数的类型，
So right off the bat, looking at the type of the function,
我能意识到，如果我抬头看，
I can just realize that if I go look up,
让我们来看看修复函子的类型。
let's go look at type of fix functor.
我们要看看 Haskell 的这个。
We're gonna look at Haskell for this one.
对不起，Elle，选择这个数据修复。
Sorry, Elle, select this one data fix.
是的。
Yeah.
所以它只是一个递归函数。
So it's just a recursive function.
我们只是每次都在外面拍这个固定的构造函数，所以
And we just slap this fixed constructor on the outside each time, so
我们可以继续递归。
that we can continue to recurse.
我们实际上编写了 catamorphism，就像为我们运行我们的应用程序一样。
And we actually write catamorphism that just like runs our app for us.
如果我看看 Haskell 中的自由 monad，
And if I look at the free monads in Haskell,
我不知道哪里有免费的控件，
I don't know where the control free,
这是一件非常相似的事情。
it's a very similar thing.
他们把它笼统地拿出来，算了。
They brought it out into a generalized, forget it.
不过是同一种类型。
It's the same type, though.
它有这个递归结构，他们刚刚在接口中释放了 monad，所以
It's got this recursive structure, they've just made monad free in interface so
很难看到。
it's hard to see.
好的。
Okay.
所以让我们回到我们的类型。
So let's get back to our types.
所以我一开始就知道，
So I know that right off the bat,
我有一个与自由 monad 兼容的类型。
I have a type that's compatible with the free monad.
但让我们现在就坚持任务
But let's just stick with task right now for
funsies 并构建最初的东西。
funsies and build out the initial stuff.
我什至不知道，也许这有效。
I don't even know, maybe this works.
让我们试一试。 [笑] 我们必须以某种方式运行我们的应用程序，
Let's give it a shot. [LAUGH] We have to run our app somehow,
对？
right?
所以让我们构建一个小小的 runApp 函数。
So let's build a little runApp function.
我们运行它的方式是我们会说， runApp(start) 作为我们的初始点。
And the way we would run this is we would say, runApp(start) as our initial point.
现在我们正在决定是否要调用这些任务或
Now we're making a decision whether or not we wanna call these tasks or
在这里传递延续。
pass the continuations here.
让我们继续，从延续开始。
Let's go ahead and start with the continuations.
我觉得那更有趣一点。
I think that's a little bit more fun.
我现在真的不知道有什么区别。
I don't really know what the difference is at the moment.
但我们只是要传递延续而不是实际任务。
But we're just gonna be passing continuations instead of the actual tasks.
这样我就得到了这个函数，如果我把这个函数称为一个任务，那么
So that way I get this function, if I call the function outcomes a task, so
f().fork(console.error) 或者我们将得到的是一个延续。
f().fork(console.error) or what we're gonna get is a continuation.
所以你可以用它运行应用程序。
So you can run the app with that.
好吧，我会将它直接传递给 runApp。
Well I'll pass it right into runApp.
我们走了。
There we go.
所以有一个循环。
So there's a loop.
因此，无论何时发生任何事情，它都会分叉任务并
So anytime anything happens, it'll fork the task and
用它持有的任何东西再次运行应用程序。
run the app again with whatever it was holding.
所以让我们试试那个节点
So let's try that out node
博客/index.js，当然。
blog/index.js, of course.
[笑] 如果你没有注意到，我在这一切中的第一步就是炸毁。
[LAUGH] My first step in all of this is to blow up, if you haven't noticed.
[笑] 所以它正在寻找我有路径情况的类型，以及 db.
[LAUGH] So it'sooking for types I got a path situation, and db.
所以只是在这件事本身上工作。
So just working in that thing itself.
好吧，酷。不要管那个。
All right, cool. Nevermind that.
所以在这里我们被要求提供我的名字。
So here we are asked for my name.
布莱恩，你今天想去哪里？
Brian, where do you wanna go today?
这很好。
This is nice.
创建作者。
CreateAuthor.
那是她的名字，布莱恩。
That's her name, Brian.
[笑] 好的，太好了。
[LAUGH] All right, great.
我的意思是，它正在工作。
I mean, it's working.
让我们多写一点这个东西。
Let's write a little bit more of this thing.
让我们说，让我们做我们的写功能。
Let's say, let's do our write function.
好吧，我们会写的，全部。
Well, we'll do write, all.
我们将完成这两个，这样我们就可以写一篇小博文了
We'll finish those two out so we can actually make a little blog post and
实际上让我们做最新的。
actually let's do the latest.
让我们不要做所有的事情，所以最新的和写的。
Let's not do all, so latest and write.
那么 write 是什么样子的呢？
So what does write looks like?
你的写作会要求
Your write is gonna ask for
标题，也许吧？
the title, maybe, right?
然后在我们给它命名之后，
And then after we give it the title,
我们必须跳到那个。
we have to kinda skip to that.
我们得再问一遍。所以我要锁链，我要问
We have to ask it again. So I'm gonna chain, I'm wanna ask for
身体。
the body.
然后从那里，我们可以链接起来，我们就有了身体。
And then from there, we can chain over and we have the body.
对不起，然后我们将把标题和正文都包起来。
Excuse me, and then we'll have the title and the body all wrapped up.
让我们把它再放到一个构造函数中，也许，
Let's put that into a constructor again composed, maybe,
而不是在那里动态创建数据类型。
instead of having just creating data types on the fly in there.
好的，整洁。
All right, neat.
然后我们把它链接起来，我们实际映射它，因为我们会
And then we just chain over that where we actually map over it cuz we will be
持有延续。
holding the continuation.
所以现在我们有一个帖子。
So now we have a post.
对不起，我忘记保存帖子了。
I'm sorry, I forgot to save the post.
让我们继续保存这篇文章。
Let's go ahead and save this post.
所以保存PostTable，我们
So save PostTable and we're
将传递给那个。
gonna pass in the post to that.
然后我们不关心帖子。
And then we don't care about the post.
我们只需要写完之后会发生什么。
We're just gonna go what happens after write.
那么最新。
So latest.
好的，很好，最新的。
Okay, great, latest.
再说一遍，我不知道这是否有效。
Now again, I don't know if this works.
我希望它有效。
I hope it works.
我认为它有效。
I think it works.
我们可能必须做到这一点。
We have to probably make this.
让我们做到这一点。
Let's make that.
所以我们需要一个 PostTable。
So we need a PostTable.
我可以给它字符串，但是
I could just give it strings, but
我们有点想在一个地方定义一些可变的表名
we're kinda wanna define some changeable table names in one spot
不必到处更改它们，而是更新。
instead of having to change them all over the place, the updates.
我们曾经在我们的身体里称谓
And we ever title in our body and
我们将再次将其包装在标题和正文中。
we'll just again just wrap it in a title and body.
我认为我们有一些时间之后的下一步是
And I think one of our next steps after this we have some time was
使用我们制作的有趣的小验证库来验证它。
validate it with our fun little validation library we made.
伟大的。但我更关心转弯
Great. But I'm more concerned about turning
这东西变成了最好的架构应用程序，对吧？
this thing into the best architected app, right?
我现在不太在意这些小细节。
I don't really care so much about the little details at the moment.
那么最新的，最新的是什么样子的？
So latest, what does latest look like?
这个很有趣。
This one's interesting.
我想我们每次都必须得到所有。
I guess we have to get all everytime.
这有点有趣。
That's a little interesting.
我们可能不得不喜欢缓存结果或向其中传递一些内容。
We might have to like cache the results or pass something into it.
让我们来看看。
Let's look at that.
我们首先说我们会得到所有（PostTable）。
We'll start by saying we'll get all(PostTable).
然后我会得到最后一个因为我们很便宜[笑]。
And then I'll just get the last cuz we're cheap [LAUGH].
帖子然后我不知道。
Posts and then I don't know.
让我们为此引入兰达 [笑]。
Let's just bring in randa for that [LAUGH].
最后来自兰达，为什么不呢？
Last from randa, why not?
为什么我们在 JavaScript 中不能使用它？
Why isn't it available to us in JavaScript?
我不确定。
I'm not sure.
好的。
Okay.
我们不会链接，我们会映射获取最后一个帖子。
We're not gonna chain, we're gonna map get the last post.
然后我想我们想以一种或另一种方式为屏幕格式化。
And then I guess we wanna format that's for the screen in one way or another.
我们将继续打印。
And we're gonna go ahead and print that.
好的，所以它是 print(formatPost) 你知道吗？
All right, so it's print(formatPost) you know what?
首先我们将映射格式，然后我们将映射打印。
First we'll map format, then we'll map print.
事实上，如果你想链接印刷品，
And actually if you wanna chain the print,
因为打印一个具有破坏性的函数。
cuz prints a function that will be destructive.
最后，我们必须映射延续。
And finally, we have to map the continuation.
在我们最新的之后会发生什么？
What happens after our latest?
我想我们回到菜单。凉爽的。
I guess we go back to menu. Cool.
函数式编程，你们都不难。
Functional programming, y'all it's no hard.
[笑] 所以让我们继续完成 formatPost 和
[LAUGH] So let's go ahead and finish the formatPost and
打印功能，我想我们可能有一些工作。
the print function and I think we might have a thing working.
缺点格式Post。
Cons formatPost.
现在，这不属于这里。
Now, this does not belong here.
我们有点像控制器，对吧？
We're kind of in a controller, right?
我不想在我的控制器中间格式化帖子。
I don't wanna be formatting posts in the middle of my controller.
我只是把它写在这里，然后我们会移动它。
I'm just gonna write it here and then we'll move it.
但是搬东西很便宜。
But moving stuff is cheap.
人们开始构建他们的文件夹结构、对象和东西。
People get so into architecting their folder structures and objects and stuff.
我怀疑这是因为他们没有制造任何便携的东西。
And I have a suspicion it's because they're not making anything portable.
我们所有的东西都是便携式的，您只需复制、粘贴和移动它等等。
All of our stuff is portable, you just copy and paste and move it and whatever.
所以对我们来说，把所有东西都扔在这里并
So it's much less of an issue for us to just throw everything here and
然后再组织起来，事后看来是 2020 年，对吗？
then organize it later and hindsight is 2020, right?
好的，formatPost 发个帖子然后
All right, formatPost takes a post and
让我们继续，只是它是 post.title 和
let's just go ahead and just it's the post.title and
post.body 一点。
the post.body a little.
我有点喜欢标题新行正文。
I little bit like title new line body.
凉爽的？
Cool?
我们很冷静，我们很好？
We cool with that, we're good?
有人吗？
Anybody?
[笑] 好的，最后一张是印刷品。
[LAUGH] All right, last one is print.
让我们打印。
Let's make print.
这将需要一些字符串。
And that will take some string.
我们要做一个 Task(rej, res) 和
And we're just gonna make a Task(rej, res) and
res(console.log)，它不是字符串。
res(console.log), which is nothing string.
了不起。
Terrific.
好的，复制那个。
Okay, copy that.
我知道我知道。那里，那里。
I know, I know. There, there.
很酷，所以看看会发生什么。
Cool, so see what happens.
名称？
Name?
布莱恩。
Brian.
你想去哪里？
Where do you wanna go?
你今天想去哪里？
Where do you wanna go today?
我们写怎么样。
How about we write.
标题。
Title.
好的，第一次发帖。
Okay, First Post.
身体。
Body.
大家好，我很兴奋，这是我的博客 [笑]。
Hello y'all, I'm so excited, this is my blog [LAUGH].
所以我只是想玩得开心。
So I'm just gonna have fun with this.
好的，是的，我认为它有效。
Okay, and yeah, I think it works.
所以它要求标题，要求正文。
So it asks for the title, asks for the body.
然后它写了标题和正文，新行。
And then it wrote the title and the body, the new line.
很难说[笑]发生了什么。
It’s just hard to tell [LAUGH] what happened.
所以也许我们会在我们的格式上做更多的工作。
So maybe we will work a little bit more on our formatting.
但这一切都会过去的。
But it’s all going.
好的。
All right.